<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of the lawful and vnlawful vsurie amo[n]gest Christians, added by Wolfgang Muscul vnto the ende of his booke vppon the Psalmes</title>
            <title>De usuris ex verbo Dei. English</title>
            <author>Musculus, Wolfgang, 1497-1563.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1556</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07941</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18310</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105482</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841210</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841210</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176620</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07941)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176620)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 557:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of the lawful and vnlawful vsurie amo[n]gest Christians, added by Wolfgang Muscul vnto the ende of his booke vppon the Psalmes</title>
                  <title>De usuris ex verbo Dei. English</title>
                  <author>Musculus, Wolfgang, 1497-1563.</author>
                  <author>T. L., fl. 1556.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>H. Singleton?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Wesel? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1556?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: De usuris ex verbo Dei.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>At end, with caption title: An aduertismente of the translatoure. T.L.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E.</note>
                  <note>Some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Interest --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Usury --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:176620:1"/>
            <p>Of the communion goſpel, and the ſcriptures of . god, are vntrue? God forbidde . Prieſt. Truly yonge man, I am ſorye for you. I am affrayde that I ſhall bee fayne to put you vp to my Lorde: then are ye vndone
. Prentyſe. Dooe as ye ſhall thynke beſte. Fare ye well maſter perſon: God open youre hearte.</p>
            <p>Be aſhamed of your doings ye Papyſtes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176620:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Of the lawful and vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful vſurie amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt Chriſtians, added by Wolf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gang Muſcul vnto the ende of his booke vppon the Pſalmes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:176620:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176620:2"/>
            <head>¶ The Preface.</head>
            <p>AMo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt other euils of this preſent tyme, alſo peſtilente vſurie is ſoo farre growen and towardes the vengeance of God, that I maye thincke it altogether in vaine too ſpeake any thinge agaynſt it, yea, though it were ſpoken with much earneſtnes, and ſingular endeuer.</p>
            <p>For we haue knowen by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that this euill did then ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially encreaſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as in our time it began to be openly blaſed &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by the preachinges &amp; wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges of godly learned men: that almooſt euen as the diſeaſe of the Canker, after cuttinge groweth &amp; ſpredeth more hurtfulli tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afore ſo after iuſte and deſerued repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge <pb facs="tcp:176620:3"/>is thys becomen vncurable and mooſt noiſome.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I mighte well bee thought to looſe my labor, and as it is ſayde by a prouerbe, to waſh tyle ſtones, if I were not bonden by promes, and forced by letters of my brethren.</p>
            <p>Therefore that I maye in anye wyſe kepe promes, and pleaſe my brethren, I will ſoo farre ſpeake of vſurie, as maye bee profitable vnto them that be godlye, and as yet not ſo much infected with this peſtilente diſeaſe, as is paſte all hope. I know at what tymes, and by what perſons there hathe ben diſputations concernynge vſurie, not onely in Germany, but alſo in the ſcholes of other contries: but I will not meddel with ſcholerly ſhredinges, that be as faſte intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled one with an other, as the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <pb facs="tcp:176620:3"/>of vſurie it ſelf is inwrapped together, but I will ſimply vtter thoſe thinges, whiche are mete to be ſpoken, withoute anye cumbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous contention.</p>
            <p>Fyrſte I wil tell what vſurie is. And then that it may be ſene, if it can be lawful vntoo Chriſtians, I will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferre it with the doctrine of Chryſte, and with the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſten religion.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:176620:4"/>¶ Of the lawefull and vnlawful vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. </head>
         <byline>Vvolfgang Muſculus.</byline>
         <div type="part">
            <div type="section">
               <head>☞ What is vſurie.</head>
               <p>LEſt that anye man might accuſe me as a mainteiner of vſurie, I wil bring a definition of vſury, not now deuiſed of my felſe, but long ago ſetforth by them, whoſe godlines in Chriſtes church hath gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch authorite, as can not be roted out by vſurers, or by theyr defenders.</p>
               <p>Hierom vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ezechiel in his .6. boke doeth write thus. Some me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thinke vſurie to be only in monei, <pb facs="tcp:176620:4"/>the which thinge godly ſcripture foreſeing doth take awai the ouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plus of euery thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, ſo that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> maiſt not receiue more than thou haſt ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen. Alſo other, for money put too vſury, are wont to take littell gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of diuers ſortes of thinges: &amp; they do not vnderſtande that the ſcripture calleth vſurie and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus, whatſoeuer thing it be, that they take more, beſides y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche they did geue. Theſe be Hiero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſaienges. Ambroſe of Nabuthe, ſayeth. Many fleinge the precep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the law, when thei haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered their monei vnto marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, do not exact vſurie in money, but of their wares thei take in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure as of vſures. Therfore let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hear what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law ſaieth. Thou ſhalt not take vſurie of meates, nor of any other thinge. Therefore meat is vſurie, and apparell is vſurie, <pb facs="tcp:176620:5"/>and whatſoeuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth too the ſtocke is vſurie, and what name ſoeuer thou wilt geue it, vſurie it is. So ſayeth Amb. Auguſtine alſo vppon the
.36. Pſalme. defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vſurie after this ſorte. If thou commit vſurie to a man (that is to ſay) if thou lende thy monei, of whome thou lokeſt too receyue any thyng more than thou haſte geuen, not onely money, but anye thinge more than thou haſt geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if it be wheat, if it be Wyne, if it be Oyle, if it be anye maner of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, if thou loke to receiue more than thou haſte geuen, thou arte an vſurer, and in that too bee diſalowed. Thus ſayeth he. Therefore, accordinge vnto theſe mennes ſayinges: Vſurie is, not oneli to take, but alſo to hope and loke for any thinge, beſides that which is called the ſtocke: that is <pb facs="tcp:176620:5"/>to ſaye, beſides that which is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, vnder what name ſo euer it be cloked. For the change of the name, doeth not take awaye the wickedneſſe of the vice which abideth.</p>
               <p>And it is euidente in the .18. of Ezechiel, that that is vſurie, what ſoeuer is taken beſides the ſtock, when as the Prophet ſayeth: He lendeth nothinge vpon vſurie, he taketh nothinge ouer. For as D. Kimhi doeth wel declare, what it is to lende vpon vſurie, it is expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded by that whiche foloweth, where it is added: he hathe taken nothinge ouer. And ſo is it redde in the .25. of Leuit. Thou ſhalt not take of him vſurie, and anye thinge ouer, but thou ſhalte feare thi God. Thou ſhalt not geue him thy money vpon vſurie, thou ſhalt not geue thy meat to receiue more <pb facs="tcp:176620:6"/>ouer. Alſo Ceſars lawes in the boke of vſurie, in like manner call vſurie, whatſoeuer is taken beſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the ſtocke: howbeit thei ſuffer the vſe of it after a ſorte, of the which we ſhal ſpeak afterwards. It is called vſura in latin, becauſe for the vſe of money a certain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>penſe is receiued, wherby there returneth ſome vantage vnto the vſurer. The Grecians call it Tocon, as a chylding or ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the money ſtocke. In Hebrue it is named Neſchech, of byting, becauſe at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt it biteth him, which payeth va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage. Thus much is now ſayd, to ſhewe what vſurye is.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>☞ Wether vſurie bee law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or not.</head>
               <p>WE do ſeke here too knowe not of vſurie of vſuries, whiche the Iewes dooe vſe, of the whyche noo <pb facs="tcp:176620:6"/>man doubteth, but that it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull and abominable, &amp; in no wiſe to be ſuffered: but of ſymple vſurie, by the whiche more is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> than geuen, whether it be muche or littell, whether it bee done in money, or in other thinges. For this vſurie ſome men ſuppoſe not to be vnlawfull of it ſelfe, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte it too be made vnlawfull by vnlawful circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces. I deny not that there may be fonde a kind of vſuri, which is not vnlawful, but profitable: ſuche is that vſurie, whiche is called earth vſurie, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which much more is receiued, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was bi ſowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted. This vſurie doth he geue, whiche geueth vnto all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all things, &amp;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, hath neuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſſe. That vſuri is ſo geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that it hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nothinge the geuer, &amp; muche profitteth the receyuer, and is not to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned of couetouſnes, <pb facs="tcp:176620:7"/>but rather by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of great good will and excellent well doinge is muche to be prayſed.</p>
               <p>Beholde, here is a kinde of vſurie for the, lawfull, profitable, and godly, by the which Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Iſaac became ryche. By thys ſome tymes thirty folde, ſome ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes ſixty fold, and ſome times an hundreth folde, without ſinne is bothe geuen of God, &amp; alſo recey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued of man. This vſurie did oure forfathers much vſe, which nowe is rekened vile, &amp; forced too geue place vnto the damnable vſurie of money. And there is an other cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vſurie, by the whiche without any ſinne, a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maye take an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth for one. This Chriſt hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſted of his father, as a ſhuerti doeth promiſe vnto his faithfull, ſaying: And eueri one, which ſhal leaue houſe, or brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or ſiſters, <pb facs="tcp:176620:7"/>or father, or mother, or wife, or ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, or fyldes, for my name, ſhall receiue an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth fold &amp; poſſeſſe life euerlaſting. Mat .19. Behold an other &amp; a heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly kind of vſuri, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche we be called &amp; not feared fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it. But I pray you, ſee how many there be, whiche ſette their minds to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gethering of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly riches, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo great gaines?</p>
               <p>By theſe exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of vſurie it is proued, not to be vnlawefull of it ſelf, to reſtore more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, or els to receiue more than thou haſt geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſam ſorte of vſurie, which in our tyme hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vpperha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which at this time we ſpeake, haue the ſame reaſon, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the vſurie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly vſurie hath, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche God him ſelf is
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> greateſt vſurer of all other, this nowe muſte bee ſpied with ſimple &amp; pure eies:</p>
               <p>They, which defend cuſtomable <pb facs="tcp:176620:8"/>vſurie, doe deuiſe manye thinges which thei mai ſhewforth, &amp; wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by thei mai be bold to ſai, that it is not vnlawful. Thei bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law out of the boke, called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> code in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of vſures, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, yea ordeined y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth, &amp; the halfe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hundreth &amp;c. &amp; they thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authorite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ciuill law maketh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, which thei do, either not to be vſurie, or if it be vſurie, not to be vnlawful vſurie: we au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the law maker was forced of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſite, not to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vſurie, but too ſet ſome ſtai of exceding couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which thing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> text of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe it ſelf proueth, for it taketh awaye great hurtfulnes of vſury, &amp; apoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meaſures, ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which nothing mai be claimed. His de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire was without dout, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie might preuail amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as ſhuld leaue no place vnto vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: but for becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> couetouſnes <pb facs="tcp:176620:8"/>did grow paſt meaſur, he iudged it nedefull y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhuld be kept in by latiſes or railes, &amp; therfore he cut awai y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hurtfulnes of vſurie, euen vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> middeſt of it. Wherefore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law doeth not maintein vſurie, &amp; make it lawful, but rather witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> charite amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s was waxe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cold, &amp; moſt filthi &amp; abomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble couetouſnes growe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo farre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it muſt be kept vnder, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperor. And ſo as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of diuorce, made by Moiſes, dyd not excuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iew afore god, which vſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law as to be giltles of brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king wedlock: likewiſe this ciuill law doth not make vſuri ſo lawful y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mai vſe it withoute offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce afore god. As Chriſt ſpake vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of diuorce: It was not ſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginninge, &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hardnes of your harts, Moy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes did ſuffer a byll of diuorce, &amp; ſo ſente them back vnto the fyrſte begynninge of lawfull wedlocke, <pb facs="tcp:176620:9"/>vnto the which thei ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfs: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo in this caſe or cauſe of vſurie, we chriſtians muſt loke vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purenes, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, righteouſnes and equite of chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is to be ſene Math .5. &amp; Luc .6. &amp; we muſt not loke vnto the ciuil lawes. For thei are not made for chriſtie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, whiche haue no nede of ciuill lawes, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei there by ſhould be ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their couetous deſire, leſt that the breake &amp; leape ouer the border of meaſure. For they are ſo gyded by the ſpirit of loue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei loue their neighbor hartely, &amp; are ready to beſtow vppon him, not onely their money, but if nede be, euen their life alſo. Where as this loue preuaileth, there canne be no place for anye coueteouſnes: nor there is no reaſon or cauſe for any ſuche lawes to be eſtabliſhed by <pb facs="tcp:176620:9"/>the whiche coueteouſnes maye be meaſured. Wherefore the minde of the lawemaker was not too mainteyne him, which in lending requireth vſurie, but too prouide for him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> boroweth: le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> becauſe he is oppreſſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nede, he ſhould be forced to borow monei, &amp; then by the vnſatiable couetouſnes of vſurers, he ſhoulde be vtterly pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and ſpoyled, when as charite is ſo colde, that he can fynd none, that wil lend frely without vſury. Wherfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> law, made by a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperour, concerninge vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, is a plaine profe, that loue of neyghbors was waxe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cold, to the great ſhame of the chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> name: &amp; ſo it is far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> excuſing of vſurye, in any ſuch ſort as to make it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are in caſe, partly by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inward gyding of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holi goſt &amp; partly by the lighte &amp; authorite of gods word, to be called fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all <pb facs="tcp:176620:10"/>thoſe thynges, whiche dyſpleaſe god: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they nede not by any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtraynt of Emperours lawes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be forced or feared. Cyuyl lawes do not forbyd al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be vnlawful afore god: &amp; what thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs they forbyd not thoſe things they punyſh not: howbeit therby it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be proued, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al thyngs ar law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful afore god, which ar not forbid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs by ciuil laws. They do not forbid anger, indignacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacyence, enuy, hate, pryde, euill luſts, couetouſnes &amp; ſuch other as the Apoſtle calleth the dedes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, and ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they do ſhit out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god al thoſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue ſuch minds.<note place="margin">Gala
.5.</note> Wherfore no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that doth any ſuch thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge is therfore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed a fore god, becauſe he is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned by any ciuil law.
<note place="margin">☞</note>Agayne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ciuill lawes do not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde al thoſe things, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are requiſite vnto true rightuouſnes. No ciuill law <pb facs="tcp:176620:10"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth fayth, hope, loue of god &amp; thy neibor, pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſite, ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tilnes, meknes, lowlines &amp; modeſty &amp;c. Whervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold ſuppoſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is not bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto theſe, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if he be otherwyſe diſpoſed, he is bi no ciuil lawes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned. Further<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>more they ſuffer ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e things for cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tain cauſes, which y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g afore god be vnlawfull, &amp; by gods word ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned. They doe ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not as in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfs right &amp; law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs may be ſhut out &amp; diſplaced. So thus far alſo thei ſuffer vſury, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a meaſure of co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uetouſnes mai be limited. Thei do not poniſh whordo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, nor take not awai y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtewes: yet therbi no whor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger is excuſed afore god, nor y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle is not made of none effect Ebr .13. Wedloke is hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable &amp; holy but whoremongers and adultrers the lord ſhal iudge. <pb facs="tcp:176620:11"/>Lyke wyſe al thoſe threatnyngs, whych in holy ſcripture co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne vſurers, be not therefore made of none effect, becauſe they bee not condemned by ciuill lawes, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of ciuill lawes is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dered: and we muſte not thynke that they are made to make men ryghteous afore god, but to kepe men ſome what in a tollerable or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, liuing together, and that the malice of man ſhould be reſtrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned wythin ſome border. Theſe woulde I knitte vp in fewe wordes, for an anſwere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, whyche by the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence of ciuil lawes do ſo defend y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſury of our times, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they denie it to be vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full afore God.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:176620:11"/>
            <head>¶ Howe a manne ſhoulde lende accordynge vnto the doctryne of Chryſte.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuche as in thys place we demaunde, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther that vſurie be lawful or vnlawfull, not afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world but afore God, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the pretence of ciuill lawes, or of any ordynaunces of manne, can haue no place in this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cauſe of Chriſtian profeſſyon conſtrayneth vs to heare euen Chryſt Gods ſonne, and to learne of his mouthe, howe Chryſtians ſhould lende and not ſinne in the ſight of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord. For of this oughte we to be well perſwaded, that no thyng can be lawfully do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, which <pb facs="tcp:176620:12"/>ſtriueth againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of our ſauiour. Wherfore we muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der how vſury agreeth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſts word. But firſt I do proteſt, that I ſpeake not vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this world, but vnto faythfull men, which be perſwaded y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the doctri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of Chriſt is ſo godly, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teineth ſuch a rule of true godlyneſſe and rightuouſnes, that all they muſte nedes diſpleaſe god, which do not hartely yelde &amp; applye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues vnto it. Math .5. Thus we reade, loke not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym, that woulde bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe of thee. And Luke .6. lende, lookyng for nothyng therof. And if you ſhall lende, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence ye hope to receaue, what tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks haue ye? For ſynners lende vnto ſiners that they may receiue like. Bi theſe words Chriſt did teache his, how they ought to behaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in thys caſe, he putteth a difference <pb facs="tcp:176620:12"/>betwixt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of thys world. Firſt he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth that they do not denye hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> woulde borowe. Vnderſtande ſo, that ther be abilite for to le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. For he which hath not himſelf, how can he be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to lende vnto others? Hedoth not permit and ſuffer vnto hys, which haue the ſubſtance of this world, a liberte to lende or not to lende. That is to ſay, he ſheweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ar ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> true rightuouſnes belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng vnto the children of God, which denye to lende vnto hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nedeth &amp; aſketh. Therfore he war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth his, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they doe not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, if they wyll belong vnto him, &amp; be in the no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of gods chyldren. Thys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this world do not acknowledge, nor they ar not therto forced by ciuil lawes,
<pb facs="tcp:176620:13"/>but they wyl be at liberte to lende or not to lende: and they dooe not thynke that they ſynne, if they do denye hym that aſketh, when as they may helpe hym. Wherfore if we haue pleaſure in the profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chryſtes religion, we muſt take hede to bee otherwyſe mynded, than they be.</p>
            <p>It is a ſynne great enoughe, if we denye our help vnto him, that woulde borowe. But truelye it is farre to much, if, like as infidels, we doe not beleue any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſine to be done of vs, when as vpon a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that would borowe, we doe not beſt owe the duety of charite, as though thoſe were tryfles that Chriſt ſayeth: Deny not hym that would borow of thee. They ſaye, theſe are no commaundements, but counſels. Vnto the Iewes it is commaunded playnly Deu .15. <pb facs="tcp:176620:13"/>after this maner. If one of thi bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren, whych dwelleth within the gates of thy cite, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lande which the lord thy God ſhall geue vnto thee, come vnto pouertye, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte not harden thy hart, nor pul in thy hande: but thou ſhalt open it vnto the poore, and lend that, whych thou ſeeſt he nedeth. How then can it be, that Moſes law ſhould haue more perfect ryghteouſnes, than the goſpell of Chryſt? and that we maye freely doe,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> leaue vndone the woorke of ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> whiche thyng was not free vnto the Iewes.</p>
            <p>And then alſo if it had been ſpoken in ſtede of a counſell: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye not hym that would borowe of thee, howe is it mete for Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that Chryſtes counſel, ſo earneſtly geuen, they maye cauſe to be taken vp or down, to or froo <pb facs="tcp:176620:14"/>and to thynke that it beyng con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned ſhal not be puniſhed? He ſaith I ſpeake vnto you whyche heare. Therfore they, that wyl be hearers of Chriſte, are bounde to obey his counſel, &amp; they can not wynd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſinne and loſſe of their ſaluacion: euen as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſicke cannot neglect the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of the phiſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> domage of their helth. But in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .25. of Deut. It is manifeſt that they ſynne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to gods wil, whych denye a br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> aſkyng to borow. Leſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (ſaith he) he cry agaynſt thee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lord, and it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ſine vnto the. Afterwardes Chriſt preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth vnto his how they ought for to lend. Lend (ſayeth he) lokynge for nothing therof. The which ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ſo vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no profit, no lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kar, no gayne, beeſides y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whyche was lent, ſhold be loked for, &amp; rece<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued: <pb facs="tcp:176620:14"/>&amp; this is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is ſpecialli required of him, which deſireth to kepe his hands cleane fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnpure vſury: but that is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ful menni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of Chriſt, whiche requireth of vs by thys place, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we alſo lende vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we can not hope to receiue anye thing at all, whyche doth ſufficiently appeare, by the wordes that he addeth, when he ſayeth: if ye ſhal lend whereof ye hope to receiue again, what tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks haue ye? For ſo ſynners doe lend vnto ſiners to receiue like. See, he ſayth not to receaue vſury, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus, ſome what beſyds the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me that was lent, but to receiue lyke. Wherefore alſo here he putteth a difference betwixte his, &amp; thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do not belong vnto him: for he re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quireth his not only to le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out profet, ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſiners do y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e times but alſo with their own da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mage <pb facs="tcp:176620:15"/>and loſſe of lente money, to helpe their neighbour and brother, and ſo to lende, that they maye pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe vnto themſelues fauoure of God.</p>
            <p>Therefore here is a difference to be made betwixte the heathen and the Chriſtian. The heathen lendeth firſt vnto thoſe, that be a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble to reſtore that, whyche they haue receaued. Then vnto thoſe, whych ſome tymes haue lente or bee able to lende. Thirdlye vnto frendes and kinred. Fourthly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe, of whom ſome kyndnes may be loked for. By theſe kinds of leandyng ſynne is not commit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, howbeit as yet the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of the kingdome and ſprite of Chriſt is not expreſſed. Wherfore they that be Chryſtyans do thus lende.</p>
            <p>Firſt vnto them, that be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <pb facs="tcp:176620:15"/>to reſtore. Then vnto them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neuer did lende any thynge, nor can not geue agayne. Thyrdly not onely vnto frendes, but alſo vnto enmyes, not onely vnto kinſfolke but alſo vnto others and ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. Forthly, wheras no thankes geuyng, much leſſe any reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, can be loked for. And in doynge theſe thynges they declare them ſelues to bee in dede his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whyche bryngeth forth his ſonne ouer the good and the bad, and raynneth vpon the thankful and vnthankful: whych alſo Chryſte requireth of hys, ſaying: that ye maye be the children of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. &amp;c. Bryng therfore vnto this rule of Chriſtian righteouſneſſe thoſe, whyche lende vpon vſury, and ſee howe farre they be from the rule of Chryſtes word, which is ſo ſette vnto all Chryſtyans, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:176620:16"/>except they do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes vnto it, they ought to be rekoned amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſinners, &amp; not amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yea they bee not ſo iuſte as ſinners. For ſo much rightuouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes is attributed vnto ſynners, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lend w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out vſury, &amp; that they deſier to receiue nothinge in the ſted of lukar, but onely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche they did lend. Therefore by thys confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, we, whych loke vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rightuouſnes of Chryſtes kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of chriſtes words, and vnto the profeſſyd of chriſtian religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may eaſely iudge how vnlawful vſury is vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whych haue yelded them ſelues vnto chryſte, and would be taken to be chryſtyans. It is not belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng vnto vs to iudge others. It belongeth to a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to anſwer to his profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; not otherwiſe to iudge of things, whether they <pb facs="tcp:176620:16"/>lawful or vnlawful, but acording to the preſcription of Chriſts doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine: and not ſo to behaue hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the triall of rightuouſnes as afore a worldly iudge, but as in the ſight of god, that he may be quitt of vnrightuouſnes. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore agreably wyth holye ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Chryſtes wordes we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clude, that that vſury, which mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueylouſly in thys laſt time hath growen in the church of Chriſt, is not lawfull but damnable and very farre from the profeſſion of Chryſts rightwiſnes. How wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked a thyng vſury is to be ſeen in it ſelfe, any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may eaſely iudge excepte onelye ſuche menne, as thinke the ſauour of lukar to bee ſwete, of what thyng ſoeuer it is gotten, the eies of whoſe myndes be vtterly blinded wyth the loue of couetouſues. <pb facs="tcp:176620:17"/>Firſt, the vice of couetouſneſſe hath euer been iudged moſt vyle, not onely amongeſt Chryſtyans, but alſo amongeſt heathens. And that is the rote of vſurye. Take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of money &amp; couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; we ſhal haue no vſurers in Chriſtes churche. Secondarelye, who doeth not ſee, howe wicked a thyng it is, to hunte for gayne, gotten by the laboure and ſwete of others? For vſurie, whyche is geuen, commeth not of the care &amp; trauell of the vſurer, but of hym, that payeth, foenus, vantage.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, thys is farre from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite, that the vſurer, wythout a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny loſſe or danger of his mony, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiueth lukar, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is in dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of no da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mage, what ſoeuer cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dice co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſerable ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which paieth vſurie, is forced to beare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe of miſfortune and
<pb facs="tcp:176620:17"/>chance. He hath all the hurte that happeneth, the vſurer hath no thyng but the gayne that is taken, and the ſtoke that is ſaued.</p>
            <p>Fourthly: Thys is alſo more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, that howe greate vſurie, and how many yeares ſo euer the det<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter paieth, yet not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding the whole ſtok remaineth &amp; is nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g leſned or worne by occupyinge. But howe ſore theſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges dooe greue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mind, &amp; decaye the abilite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> payer, I nede not to geue ani aduertiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſeyng by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he that is in ſuch caſe, perceaueth that thys pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t euil can not be ouercome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being vtterly diſcouraged he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh wyfe &amp; childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; leaueth what other goods ſo euer he hath vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnſaciable viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t couetous vſurer. So .1. Sam .22. We reade that they did, which oppreſſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> det co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueihed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues vnto Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid <pb facs="tcp:176620:18"/>an exile. Such ſightes, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as magiſtrates winke, godlye men beholde dayly afore theyr eies with ſorow &amp; ſighinge. And that which is moſt greuous, in the ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ſeaſon whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſuch vſurers ought to haue no place amongſt citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, then doe they inioye honours in the church and in the citie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ But the vſurer replyeth.</head>
            <p>IT is (ſaith he) common in euery mans mouth: He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is willing hath no wrong, I ſend for no man. I force no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to take money of me. Thei co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of their own accord, thei take my money, &amp; do not aſke it of any other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but only of vſury? What do I in thys caſe offende?
<pb facs="tcp:176620:18"/>Let them leaue me my money to my ſelfe, if the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mage of vſurye be ſo greuous vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I anſwer, theſe are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayinges not of a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man, but of a very heathen, yea of him that hath no mynde of man.</p>
            <p>Nede is a ſharpe ſhaft. Theſe wretches forced by nede come vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to thee, of whoſe wretchedneſſe thou cruelly &amp; filthely takeſte thy vantage. The vſurer replieth agi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e: But when as they receiued mony of me vpon condicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vſury, thei wer glad and dyd geue thankes. What iniure can thys be, whyche cauſeth gladnes and thankes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng: I anſwere, that theſe wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches reioyce &amp; geue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they doe fele a benifite, but becauſe they ſuppoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by thys do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mage of vſurye, they maye eaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greuous neceſſyte, whyche doeth oppreſſe them preſently. <pb facs="tcp:176620:19"/>Surely they deſier rather ſimpli to borow money, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to take it v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſurye. But for becauſe ſo gret inhumanite preuaileth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they can no where finde ſuch liberalite as lendeth frely, they ar glad to take money vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſury: but thys kynde of gladnes at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt turneth into greateſt heauines. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they fle fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> charibdis, thei fal into ſcil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>la, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roke into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gulfe. Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome doeth well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare this glad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of takyng vſurye moneye, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bitynge of a ſerpente called aſpis: for euen as he, whyche is bitte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Aſpis, doeth gladlye fal onſlepe, &amp; by the ſwetneſſe of deadly ſlu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber dieth, becauſe in ſle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ping y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poiſon paſſeth to euerye me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber: ſo he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> taketh money of the vſurer is preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly glad, as though he had a benefite, howbeit vſuri, hauing ſpedy paſſage to all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath, turneth all into det. And Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <pb facs="tcp:176620:19"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elder, being demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded what it was to take vſurye, anſwered, the ſame y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is to kill a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Third<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly they, which ſeme to haue ſome taſt of Chriſtes goſpel, do bryng that, not by thee which they may amende the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they would cloke their vngodly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: but al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law and the prophets, as Chriſte witneſſeth, ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what I would ſhould be done vnto me, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame I doe alſo vnto others. Vnto mi ſelf I wold wiſh no other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but for one hundreth florens, to repay euery yeare fiue. What ſine is it for me the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to take ſo much of others? For I my ſelfe take vpon thys condicion ſo oft, as nede is. So many I geue to others, and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gayne ſo many I take of others. I anſwer, it is moſte vngodlines to abuſe Chryſtes word, which ar ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to mainteine not coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes
<pb facs="tcp:176620:20"/>but brotherli loue. Thou as is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, doſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame toothers, whiche y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> requireſt of others. If y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> do this of a charitable ſprit, ſet thi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pore &amp; nedye, &amp; cloth thiſelf w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hys nede, thinking, what y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>, beyng in his caſe, woldeſt that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rich ſhold do vnto the, whether y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei, ſhold le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnto the w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vſury or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out vſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry? Vndoubtedly y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wouldeſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out vſury. For y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhoulde be more profitable vnto the, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholdeſt be burdened w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chargea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vſury. Wherfore that ſayinge of chriſt: Do vnto others, as thou woldeſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> others ſhold dooe vnto the, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> muſte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to bee ſo ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as what y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> woldeſte wiſhe do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e vnto thee, being in ſuch caſe as thi neighbour is, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame muſte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> do vnto him, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded towards thyſelf. Search thy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>n own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience &amp; iudge indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly <pb facs="tcp:176620:20"/>whether y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſt ſay truly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy pore nedy neighboure is ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued &amp; helped of thee, as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> placed in his caſe woldeſt be loued &amp; hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped of others. Wherfore ſeing y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt not truly ſay this of thyſelf, what availeth it deceitfulli to dali w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaying of Chriſt our ſauiour? Alſo y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> geueſt vſury vnto others, &amp; takeſt of others. I heare this, &amp; I beſech the tel me for what cauſe y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> geueſt: &amp; for what nede: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche they doe geue of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> takeſt? No, no. Thei beare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>age of vſury forced bi nede y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> beareſt no da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>age, but for hope of greater gai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, not for nede but for couetouſnes, geueſt .v. for an .c. to gain x. xv. xx: and y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſo geueſt &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt, as many ſacrifici<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g prieſts ar wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to offer a halpeny to kepe vp in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gaines of offering, &amp; to prouoke the people to offer by their e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple: &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wai for laie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g down one penie they take vp ten. <pb facs="tcp:176620:21"/>So very wel doe vſurers &amp; Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniaks agree, becauſe they are both caryed by one ſprite of coue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>touſnes. Forthly wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſurer feleth himſelf in a ſtrait, &amp; ſeth no way to defend vſurye, he turneth towards other artes &amp; ſaith: if v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury be ſuch a thyng,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I do ſinne if I take, then I knowe what I wyll do. I will lende no parte of my money vnto any man. I wyll kepe it vnto my ſelfe, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t that I ſhold be an vſurar. I anſwer, this is that eſcapyng of vſurye, for the which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperors lawes wolde not vtterly forbid vſury. Wilt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> kepe thy money to thy ſelf? Afore the courte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is lawful, but it is vnlawful afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> court of Chriſt, by whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not to deny him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wold borow of thee, but to lend, loki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to receaue nothyng: wherfore if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> boeſt either of theſe, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> declareſte <pb facs="tcp:176620:21"/>the ſelf not to be a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>draw lendyng vnto thy brother, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aſketh whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or whether y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſo lende as to take agayne: y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſynneſte alyke, both agaynſt Chryſt and againſt thy next brother. If thou lend no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at al, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſinneſt not in vſury: howbeit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rote of vſury, which is couetouſnes, thou noriſheſt in thi heart, and art a tranſgreſſoure of Chryſtes worde. If thou lende v<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon vſurie, then y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſynneſt againſt the commaundement of Chryſte. And to be ſhort, as much as lyeth in thee, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> deſtroyeſt thy neighbor aſwell by not lending as by len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſury. If y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>draw len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art worſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a hathen ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner: for ſinners do lende vnto ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may receue lyke. If y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> do lende for vſury, ſo art y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> worſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature kepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vice. <pb facs="tcp:176620:22"/>Fiftly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couetouſnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wil reply after thys maner: if I lende w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out vſury y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, which is mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e own ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be reſtored vnto me: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pore hath nor ſo muche, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der agayne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole ſumme. But if he ſhal geue euery yeare a certein vſury, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me parte of my mony ſhalbe reſtored vnto me I anſwere. Thou knoweſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of thy brother to be ſo great, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> borowed mony: why the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doeſt not y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> yelde vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> words of chriſt? by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which Lu .6 he ſaith: and your rewarde ſhalbe great in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And ye ſhalbee the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſte higheſt. And Luk .14. And it ſhalbe re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred vnto thee in the regeneracion of the rightuous. How doeſte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> receiue nothing, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as for earthly gaine
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, which laſteth euer, ſhal bee ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred vnto thee? Therfore this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe <pb facs="tcp:176620:22"/>is vtterlye contrarye vnto Chryſts doctrine, which teacheſh euen therfore to do good vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore, becauſe he hath nothynge to geue agayne, that the heauenly rewarde may be purchaſed. And thou euen for the ſelfe ſame cauſe wilt not lend vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pore, becauſe he hath not ſo much as to reſtore that, whiche he hath receaued of thee. Therfore ether y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doeſte not beleue that Chryſtes promyſe is true: or els y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doeſt more deſier te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral gayne, than eternal, earthly than heauenly. Sixtly. All y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue (ſayeth he) I haue gotten w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great care and trauell, wherefore then ſhoulde I beſtowe them v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon others in vayne? What is it to me, that others doe not ſo take hede vnto theyr owne, as I doe? What owe I vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? I anſwer: <pb facs="tcp:176620:23"/>Chriſt beſtowed no ſmal thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, redemyng thee vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his bloud: &amp; for thy ſake he beca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e poore to make thee rich. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what is it to Chryſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we take no better hede vnto our ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: And bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydes theſe, what thou oweſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy brother, heare the Apoſtle: Ye owe nothing vnto any manne ſayeth he, but that ye loue one an other. Ro .13. Thou oweſt therfore vnto thy nedy brother loue, &amp; alſo vnto god y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> oweſt thy ſelfe, &amp; not only money. Wherefore beecauſe Chriſt hath loued vs &amp; geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym ſelfe for vs, therfore we ought to beſtow our lyues for our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 1. Io .3. We doe all muche fayle in thys thyng, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> without the affecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of true loue, we loke vpon the ſlenderneſſe and humilite of oure brethren, &amp; not rather vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wil of god &amp; his manifeſt commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, <pb facs="tcp:176620:23"/>albeit I keepe in ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the vnmeaſurable worthynes of our free redempcion. Is the pore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnworthi, vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholdſt geue freely? But Chriſt is not vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>worthy, which requireth thys of thee. The pore hath not deſerued thys benefite. Chryſt hath deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it. Is not the poore able to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtore that, whiche he receaueth? Chriſte is able to reſtore an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth folde, and to geue life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, as he alſo hath promyſed Mat .19. Sixtly becauſe couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes is the moſt tougheſt wrange<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler, the vſurer as yet replieth, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: how ſhould I live? How ſhal I prouyde for me and myne, if I muſt ſo lend y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I receaue nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g? I anſwer, it is ſaid of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord: firſt ſeke the kyngdome of God &amp; the rightuouſneſſe thereof, and all theſe ſhalbe caſt vnto you. And
<pb facs="tcp:176620:24"/>the gentils ſeke all theſe thinges. Therfore neither doeth thys w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inge waywardneſſe belong vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to Chryſtians: neyther ought we to feare, leſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, by helpyng nedye brethren, we doe not well prouide or ſee to our own thynges. For thus we reade Pro .11. Some diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute their own and become ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cher, ſome catche that, whyche is not their own, and be euer in nede The ſoule, which bleſſeth, that is to ſay, which doth good, ſhall bee fylled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fatnes: &amp; he, whyche ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth drynke, ſhalbe ſatiſfied w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> drinke. And Eſa .58. Breake vnto the hongery (ſayeth he) thy bread and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nedy &amp; wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derers leade into thy houſe. When y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſeeſt the naked clothe him, &amp; doe not deſpice thy fleſh. When as thou ſhalte haue powred forth thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oule vnto the hongry, &amp; refreſhed the afflycted <pb facs="tcp:176620:24"/>ſoule, then ſhalt thou be as a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; as a well of waters that neuer fayll. And the Apoſtle
.2. Co .9. He hath diſperſed, &amp; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pore, &amp; hys ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes abydeth for euer. He, which miniſtreth ſede vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſower, wil alſo geue bread to be eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thful ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold not feare fallyng into pouerte by helpynge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be poore. Howbeit I would not damne it if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles ſaying might haue place: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rich ſhould help y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lacke of bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .2. Co .8. But if of neceſſaries ther wer not ſo ready geuing vnto others, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> might bee tollerable, ſo that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weaknes of fayth be not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed. But who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in ſo great riotous waſt of al things lack, is not feared, but whereas y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nedines of brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be rele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued there it is feared? <pb facs="tcp:176620:25"/>If we folowed that
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> rule, whyche is wrytten .1. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 6 after thys ſorte: hauyng what to eate, and wherwith to be clothed, let vs be contented, litell place ſhoulde remayne vnto this feare. Nature (as he ſayeth) is ſente a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with a litle, but glotony beg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth vnmeaſurably. See y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> honoſt labor bee exerciſed, idelnes auoy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, ryoteouſnes layd a ſyde, &amp; the abuſe of al thinges ſhut forth: and we ſhalbe without care vnder the protection and prouydence of God, and there ſhalbe no nede to feare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neceſſite of penurie. Now whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſo great cooſtes are beſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proude &amp; beautiful buil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinges, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> riotous apparel, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al maner of dainty meates, howe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beit I ſpeake not of innumerable other things not neceſſary, what maruel is it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pouerte is feared, if the gaine of vſurye ſhould fayle?
<pb facs="tcp:176620:25"/>Suerely he muſt ſtand in nede of many thinges, whiche fedeth and clotheth thoſe, that be hys, moſte deliciouſly and gorgiouſly.</p>
            <p>He ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in nede of many thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, whiche is purpoſed to leaue great ryches vnto his heyrs. He, that nedeth many thinges, vſeth alſo many meanes, by righte &amp; by wronge, to come to his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe thinges beinge taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, it will not ſeme very harde, neither to caſt away theſe deteſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble uſuries, neither by any mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſuccour nedy brethren.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ Of the vſurie of them, which geue their monei for vſurie, either vntoo marchauntes or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Princes.</head>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:176620:26"/>HEtherto we haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vſuri, by the which the pore is bonde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryche, &amp; the goods of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bare and nedy are ſupt vp: and of that kind of lending, bi the which Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth vs to ſuccour nedy brethren.</p>
            <p>Now muſt we ſpeake of thoſe, which haue monei by inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> otherwiſe, &amp; lend it vnto ryche men, marchauntes or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, vpon condition too receyue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery moneth, or euery yeare, ſome vſurie, the ſtocke in the mean time abiding whol, to be reſtored whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they wil cal for it. Here ſpringeth a queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what ſinne is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted in this kind of vſurie. They ſaye neither is burdened, neither he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> geueth, nor he that taketh vſurie: but by good prouiſion they haue bothe profet. He, that geueth vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, <pb facs="tcp:176620:26"/>doeth vſe his ſtocke wel, and gaineth ſo much of it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with oute any loſſe he can geue vſurie.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, he that taketh vſurie of his monei: he gathereth as it were a yearelye fruite, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any dekey of the ſtock, which bi theſe mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s he mai reſerue hole vnto his heires. When as therfore here is no hurt, howe can here be any ſinne againſte charitie? and there bee none, howe maye thys vſurie be called vnlawfull?</p>
            <p>I aunſwer. That this muſte nedes be graunted: that there is not ſo greate ſinne in thys kinde of vſurie, as in that, by the which vſurie is taken of the pore, which crueltie is forbidden, not onely, by the lawes of Chriſte, but alſoo by the lawes of nature.</p>
            <p>For it is playn cruelnes, to ſeke <pb facs="tcp:176620:27"/>after lukar, out of the labors, and calamites of the poore. Wherfore this vſurie, of the whiche we ſhall ſpeake now, differeth muche from that, which by no meanes can bee tollerable. Howbeit, in the mean ſeaſon it is not too be ſuppoſed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is nothing, whiche can be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proued in the vſurie of ryche men. For the righteouſnes of a chriſten man doth not reſt in that he doth burden no man in any bargayn or buſines. Wherefore we muſte ſe, whiche be the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtances of this vſurie, for the which it may not be commended.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt, this I ſuppoſe is ſure: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is in both, as wel in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, as in hym that taketh vſurie, a reſpect of priuate profet. For neither the one for brotherly loue le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth out his money vnto a riche marchaunt, but for too receyue of <pb facs="tcp:176620:27"/>it yearly or monethlye gayne: nor the other is ſo redy to geue vſury, that he wolde geue it, if he coulde kepe it with his owne aduantage. For as he ſaieth: The loue of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney groweth as much, as the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney it ſelf groweth. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge he geueth vſurie withoute wranglinge, leſt that he ſhoulde bee forced too reſtore the whole ſtocke, or to be noted of euell cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite.</p>
            <p>There be many notable exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of this matter. Therefore, ſeinge that the rote alſo of thys vſurie is the loue of priuate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, I do not ſe, howe it can agree without blemiſh vnto chriſtians, which ought to be furdeſt frome loue of priuate profet. Let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeke thoſe, whiche bee his owne, ſayeth the Apoſtle, but thoſe whiche belonge vnto others.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:176620:28"/>The loue of priuate profet, with the loſſe of others, is ſo euil that it ought not to be ſuffered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the gentils: and to gape for gaine, although it be without domage to others, yet is it a thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of it ſelf that ought to be farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſtians, euen as to liue delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telye and idely, although a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do ſo liue, not hurtinge nor hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe others. Wherfore as they ſinne, which liue delicately in the houſes of princes, of noble &amp; ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che men, albeit they fele or percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue no hurt of it: ſo a chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinneth, coueting priuate profet, albeit he go ſo aboute it, that he ſeke for hys owne gaine, not of the nede of poore men, but of the welth of the ryche.</p>
            <p>Moreouer he, that taketh vſurie, muſt take good hede, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:176620:28"/>he ſerue hys owne lack of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue or not.</p>
            <p>For it is not inough for a chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten man, ſo too deale with hys neyghboure, that he can not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne: but he muſte alſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, what fayth he hathe towarde God, and how all thynges, which he doeth, agree, or diſagree wyth ſincere faith.</p>
            <p>And to come to the trial of this matter, let hym thinke in him ſelf, which taketh vſurie, that it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to take to him ſelf his own mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nei, and to put away the gayne of vſurie. But if he fayle in faith, then ſhall he ſoone falle in theſe thoughtes. If I ſhoulde lyue not vpon vſurie, but vpon the ſtock, it coulde not ſufficientlye diſcharge my neceſſary expe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes, throughout all my life, &amp; then what coulde be
<pb facs="tcp:176620:29"/>left after my death vnto my chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and ſucceſſors? where vpon ſhoulde they liue, if I ſhould ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d all?</p>
            <p>But theſe be thoughtes not of fayth, but of miſtruſt: and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of a minde ſo geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vſury, that he ſuppoſeth, no way can be for him to liue, if he muſte forſake vſurie.</p>
            <p>But they make this obiection: That the Lorde muſt not be temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, as though it were a tempting of God by ſure truſt, accordinge to Gods worde, to hang vpon his prouidence, and to forſake y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kinde of liuing, in the whiche men lyue idely, ſeking by vſurie to haue all thinges neceſſari. If it be a temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Lorde, not to liue vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſurie: what excuſe is there for ſo many godly fathers, prophets, apoſtles and others, bothe of the <pb facs="tcp:176620:29"/>olde teſtament and of the new, as did rather ſuffer pouertie and hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> embraſe vantage of vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie? Doeth Chriſt teache this too tempt the Lord, when he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them not too gather treaſure vnto them ſelfes: and to lend, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge for nothinge therof? To tempt the Lord, is to truſte vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, where as nothing is pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſed of the Lord: and to neglect the trades of liuinge and doinge, whiche he teacheth, and too vſe other.</p>
            <p>But I finde no where, that the Lord hath promiſed too noriſhe &amp; kepe vs by vſurie in idelnes. Wherefore, this is rather a temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge of God, to liue in idelnes, &amp; alſo to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrat chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto idel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: and then to truſt, that money yelding yearly vſurie can be able continually to geue them enough, <pb facs="tcp:176620:30"/>loſe rue not onli for neceſſares, but alſo for ſuperfluous pleaſured.</p>
            <p>Wherefore alſo their reaſon is but vaine, whiche too cloke their vſurie ſaye: when as for vſurie I do committe my monei of truſte vnto others, then do I let it forth to da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. For it mai cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that the marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which vſeth my money about his marchaundyſe buſines, either by miſfortune, or els by his owne neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce fall into pouerte, and ſo my whole ſtock be loſte.</p>
            <p>Wherefore whiles fortune fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, it is not far amis that I take vſurie of him. So is the vſurer toſſed in vncertentes, and caſteth his goodes into ieoperdy, far vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like vnto them, which truſting to God occupye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfs honeſtly.</p>
            <p>Gameners alſo ieoparde their monei in vncertente, &amp; yet no wiſe man doth alow the loue of Game<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning <pb facs="tcp:176620:30"/> in a chriſten man. After this ſorte, when as thei wil not be ſuch as tempte God, thei confeſſe by woorde and dede, that they caſte their monei into vncerten ſucceſſe &amp; daungers, when thei let it forth for vſuri, and ſo thei tempt God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, thou ſhuldeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, how that riche marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or prince behaueth him ſelf, whiche payeth thee vſurie. Thou thinkeſt it is a ſufficient excuſe for vſurie, that he is not ſo poore, as by payinge of vſurie to hinder him ſelf. But if thou make a good rekeninge, thou ſhalt perceiue beſides theſe, other thinges to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>But if he laboure, by the abuſt of thy monei, to get great ryches, eyther vnto pryde and riot, or els vnto the practiſe of tirannye and warres, to lay waſte &amp; oppreſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contries, and alſo his
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ne: <pb facs="tcp:176620:31"/>then I praye the, how canſt thou glorie, that thy taking of vſurie is blame leſſe: ſeinge that for it thou arte made to ſerue other mennes ſinnes, in makinge thy money ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iect vnto ſuche me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s luſtes? Thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou, that thou mayſte frelye let out thy money vnto any vſe, ſo that it be don to thy nown gaine? Is not moneye letten oute of vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers the greateſt cauſe of riotte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes dayely increſſinge in thys our age, of pride more than is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the Heathen, of ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full idelnes of many thouſandes, of ſo many bloudy warres &amp; ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led ſubiectes? If thou be a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten man, how canſt thou kepe no rekeninge of theſe thinges?</p>
            <p>There is as it were a certen co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie betwixt them that geue, and them that take vſurie. For they lay their labors together, wherby
<pb facs="tcp:176620:31"/>thei ſerue, on either ſide, their own gaines or affections, and ſo they ioyne together one with the other to commit ſinne.</p>
            <p>It is a heauy thinge, if any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alone, and by hym ſelfe do ſinne: but howe muche more weightie ought it to be thought, if any man for priuate gaine doo ſo beſtowe his diligence towardes his neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bor, as to noriſhe him alſo in hys naughtines?</p>
            <p>Fourthly alſo this is to be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidered, how this kinde of vſurie letteth the workes of charite. As concerninge that money, which y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vſurer hath vnoccupied, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not to be beſtowed vpon any neceſſary houſhold affaires, that it do not remayne idell and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitefull, but that he maye take ſome profitte of it, he ſuppoſeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it oughte to be let oute vnto ſome <pb facs="tcp:176620:32"/>vſe. Therfore he letteth it forthe vnto vſurie, and this way he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that he doth wel prouide for his own profet. But I beſech you when ſhal he, being of this mind, help his neighbors rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de aboute him, that be pore and nedi? That, which he taketh vp of vſurie, he appointeth partly vnto neceſſary vſes, and partly vnto the gaine of vſurie, to increaſe his ſtock yearly by ſuche gaines, as he can gette. Whereof, can a man thinke, that he will geue vnto the pore: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will he frely and without vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie lend vnto the pore that aſketh: of that, of the whiche he findeth him ſelf and his: No, I ſuppoſe: wherefore ſhoulde I geue, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he, vnto others that, which I nede my ſelfe? Paul ſayeth: that youre abundaunce maye fille vp their want. Here is no abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, <pb facs="tcp:176620:32"/>all that I haue is neceſſarye. I muſt take hede too beautefie thys eſtate, whiche I
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eceyued of my ancetors, I muſt regard mi name and my honor, I muſte, as mere is, kepe my wife and chyldren not beggarly &amp; barely, but liberally. Here is nede, not of a littell and common ſumme of money, but of a greate and notable. Will he geue of that, which he appointeth vnto vſurie? No, no. Theſe he thinketh be holye thinges, not too be touched. What then remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, but that in ſuch a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of charitie be ſuppreſſed by di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligence to get monei: eſpecially if this vſurie be thought not vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a mind, poſſeſſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loue of monei, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be nipped w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no feli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of ſinne, but as in a lawful matter thinketh there is no daunger.</p>
            <p>And ſo we heare theſe aunſwers, <pb facs="tcp:176620:33"/>when as any thinge is aſked to be borowed of ſuche men: I wolde lende ſaye thei, if I had money in a redines, but at this time I haue no monei, wherfore ye muſt be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent, albeit ſo I lende nothinge.</p>
            <p>So thei neglect and excuſe a dede of charitie. But why haue they no money at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de? Therfore, becauſe parte is appointed vnto houſhold and dayly charges, part to enrich and increſſe the ſtocke,</p>
            <p>And hereof we ſe it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth oft to paſſe, that thei which be ſo min<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſurie, do not out of ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d paye the hire, which thei owe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto ſmiths, neither vnto tai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers, neither vnto ſhomakers, but ſuffer it certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> years to growe into great ſummes, leſt that they ſhuld be conſtrained to cut of ani portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of monei, belonging either vntoo vſurie, or vnto the familie: howe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoever <pb facs="tcp:176620:33"/> thoſe worke men, unto the whiche thei be indetted, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mean time be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at home with nede oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed. What thinge can be deuiſed worſe than this is?</p>
            <p>Therfore, if thoſe be wel weyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed, whiche I haue heretofore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, that is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, how this vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is the nori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ente of pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>te profet, and ſerueth incredulite &amp; miſtruſte vntoo ſuch abuſes, as monei let out vnto vſurie ſerueth, and how that the dedes of charite be diſtroyed, by deſire, to gather monei: I thinke that it is euident enough, that this vſurie, which is exerciſed amongeſt ryche men, as thoughe it were lawefull, can not be alowed of them, which knowe what is required of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> profeſſors of chriſten faith, which bear ſuch a badge of brotherly charitie, and of contempte of ryches earthely, <pb facs="tcp:176620:34"/>that withoute them, they can not be counted to be chriſtians.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ Of the vſurie of wydowes and the fatherles.</head>
            <p>THey, that be tutors either of widowes or of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therles moue here a queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, concerning ſuch mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney as is not their owne, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth by enheritance vnto wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and orphanes, whether it be lawfull for them to let out that monei vnto vſurie, and deliuer it to be vſed of them, which without their owne hinderaunce may yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely repay ſome vſurie. They ſaye the monei is not oures, but we be truſted with it. That, whiche we do, is not for our owne gaine, but for the widowes and fatherleſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:176620:34"/>Wherefore we are not in this too be blamed, as thoughe by takinge vſurie, we ſeke oure owne. For we ſeke not our owne, but the profet of others, widowes &amp; fatherles: and ſo we fulfil the worke of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, and we do as we are bonden by promes vnto them.</p>
            <p>I aunſwere: I know that thys was a cuſtome amongeſt oure fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, afore peſtilente vſurie had defiled the church, that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted vnto widowes &amp; orpha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, which was permitted vnto none other. All vſurie was called euil, except that of widowes &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therles. At the laſte, all the gates were opened vnto this euell, and gaine of vſurie graunted too anye man. But how wel widowes and orphanes were prouided for, the corruption of the times folowing doeth euidently witnes. There
<pb facs="tcp:176620:35"/>coulde haue ben brought no euill more noyſomme into the churche of Chriſte, by the whiche after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the goodes of widowes &amp; fatherles began miſerably too be waſted. For when as the fyre of vſurie hath eaten vp all the welth of a familie, after the death of the father of the familie, what rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant remaineth vnto widowes &amp; fatherles, that maye be lette oute vnto vſurie.</p>
            <p>Should it not haue ben better for the prouiſion of widowes &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fatherles, if liberte of vſurie cold no where haue hadde any place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s? Nowe, becauſe gaine of vſurie is crepte in vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of widowes &amp; orpha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, vnto them can not come of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of theſe times anye ſo greate gaynes, as hurt and hinderaunce, that is ſpronge oute of that ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce <pb facs="tcp:176620:35"/>of oure ancitours.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, it is euidente e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough by reaſon of that ſuffera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that vſurie was not therfore ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red vnto widowes and fatherles, becauſe it was lawefull: for if it had ben taken as lawfull and fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teles, wherfore ſhould there haue ben any ſuffera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and permiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? but for that, which was vnlawful vnto others, was thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch ſort it might be ſuffred vnto wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and fatherles, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite the mother of all liberalite, began in the churche, not onely to waxe colde and fruiteles, but vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly dead and vanquiſhed.</p>
            <p>But, &amp; if the apoſtles precept, concerninge widowes .1. Timo
.5. had ben kept, certenly thei mighte farre better, &amp; more chriſtian like haue ben prouided for, than by ſufferance of vnlawfull vſurie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:176620:36"/>If a yonge woman were a wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, ſhe ſhould be occupied with ſome honeſt labor, and being of a baſſe ſtocke, ſhe ſhould be either a waiting, or a bonde ſeruaunt vnto her ancientes, vntill ſuche time as God did geue good occaſion of conuenient mariage. If ſhe were olde, ſhe ſhould liue ſimply of her owne, ſo longe as her owne good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des did laſte: and after that they were ſpent, ſhe ſhould be fonde of her kinſfolke, or if thei were not able, then ſhould ſhe liue vpon the churche goodes, accordinge to the cuſtom of the Apoſtolical church. When as at the beginning of the growinge of the church by faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full contributors churche goodes were laid together, how were thei the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſpoſed? Thei were diuided, accordinge vnto euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s nede, and were not let oute vnto vſurye
<pb facs="tcp:176620:36"/>for gains. That ſimplicite did wel agree with faithfull chriſtianite: and did muche comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> charite, by the which badge Chriſts ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers are knowen. But now in thys vſurers world and ſeaſon, howe faithfully the nede of widowes &amp; fatherles is prouided for, it is by ouer many exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples daili declared.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, that vſurie might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely be ſuffered, by the which it is thought that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nede of widowes, fatherles and power hoſpitals be prouided for, if the confuſe heape of other vſuries and vnlawefull bargens mighte bee vtterly taken awaye, either by the authorite of gods worde amongeſt them, that wil be taught to feare God, or els by the power of the magiſtrates, whiche ought in theſe aſſembles, ſummoned by the Emperor, not to be leſte regarded: if, as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <pb facs="tcp:176620:37"/>tended, ſo ther be indede any ſeki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of chriſtes church.</p>
            <p>Wherefore it is hartelye to be wiſhed, that if all vſurie ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly be ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>niſhed oute of Chriſtes church: yet at the leſte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie be not ſuffered, by the whiche the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of pore men be miſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rably, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trari vnto chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> charite, pilled and piked, yea, ſupt vp and deuoured: I mean y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vſurie, which the ryche doth require and take of him, whome he knoweth to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to beare the hinderaunce of vſurie, and vnto whome throughe the affection of true loue, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſentence of Chriſt our ſauioure, he oughte either by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge or lendyng to ſtreach forth hys handes, not too ſpoyle, but to helpe.</p>
            <p>Againſte this kinde of vſurie: The Canoniſt haue apointed certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <pb facs="tcp:176620:37"/>penaltes beſydes gods poniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which the vſurers deſerue. Firſte that they bee noted of infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, wyth infamye of the lawe, and that alſo by the ciuil lawe as wel as by the canon law. Further<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>more that they bee not admytted vnto the communion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church. Thirdly that they be imbarred of buriall belongynge vnto Chryſts churche.</p>
            <p>Fourthly that theyr teſtamentes and willes be of no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e effect by any law, wyth manye others ſuche kyndes of iuſt penaltes. But theſe haue remayned in papers, and in the meane ſeaſon vſurers in the church haue honors wyth vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful gotten goods. And ſuche vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamfaſtnes hath preuayled vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> manye magiſtrates, princes, &amp; other great perſonages doe geue liberte vnto the Iewes, <pb facs="tcp:176620:38"/>in their dominions to exercyſe not only ſimple vſurye, but alſo that, which is named vſury of vſurers &amp; they doe not onely geue licence, but they alſo let out houſes, &amp; bar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for certayne exaction, what they ſhall yearely paye for liberte to exercyſe vſury, &amp; moſte vnrighteouſly they force their ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectes to be bounde to paie ſuche vſuries. And here is ſetled that biſhoplike correction, which par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doneth raue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and plageth doues But here we make an ende of thys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vſury. For as I ſaid of the firſt it myght wel be thogh great folye, to be muche occupyed in ſuch a mater, that, beynge lyke vnto the gowte, can be helped by no handes of any ſurgery. Thys euill is waxen ſo bygge, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> admonition of many good menne it is beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e vncurable. For it hath <pb facs="tcp:176620:38"/>corrupted euen the crownes of the heades of thoſe, whyche oughte by their autorite to haue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtande ſuch corrupcyon, and to haue kept and ordered the other lower mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers in the trade of true righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. It is Chryſtes ſaying: If the ſalt be vnſauery, what ſhalbe ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned therwyth? alſo: Ye are the light of the world. If the lyght, whych is in you, be darknes, how great ſhal the darknes of the bodi be? Ther remayneth nothyng els, but that we loke for the hande of the Lorde, whyche ſoone ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moue oute of the churche all kynde of corrupcion. The Lorde come at once, and deliuer his Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:176620:39"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> An ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſmente of the tranſlatoure. T. L.</head>
            <p>LOncernyng lendyng, here maye any man eaſelye ſee, who, what, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and to what ende Chryſte hath taughte and commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to lend. Firſt he that hath receyued any ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lent at the Lordes hands, he him ſelfe muſt put it forth. Math .25. Luke .19. For if he doe not occupy it, then ſhal it be taken from hym and he be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned for not vſing of it. Alſo he that hath, muſt dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe of that, whych he hath, vnto hym that lacketh. Luke
.3. And the ende of doyng good and lendyng vnto hym, that lacketh &amp; nedeth,
<pb facs="tcp:176620:39"/>muſt not be to hope or looke for glory, gayne or any thing thereof vnto hym ſelfe. Luke .6. So he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath but onli to find his wife, chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; family, or but only a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſtocke for his own trade in his own vocacion: he muſt, as the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer lendeth his ſede vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, ſo w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce lay forthe &amp; lend, he himſelfe hys owne ſtocke to hys own occupying. And he, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beſydes ſuche a ſtocke hath any more he muſt reſerue and kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſidew to be in a readynes to bee geuen in almes, or ſent to releue o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be nedy. And thys beyng done to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god may be glori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied, &amp; the nedye releued, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny lokynge for of glorye or gayne worldly to himſelf, he ſhal be ſure to fynde thys a verye profitable and godly vſury: but if any man for worldly police, priuate profet <pb facs="tcp:176620:40"/>or vayne glory, do pull from the finding of his familie, from the maintenaunce of his own exerciſe in hys own trade, or from the cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritable relief of the nedy, to lend vnto the riche and welthy, that is vncharitable, vnlawfull and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly. I doe not thynke that by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſellyng, lendynge or ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng, or any indifferente bargey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge amongeſt welthy rich men is euill: but as concerning vſurye I aduertiſe al them, that be wiſe and wel learned in other matters &amp; yet cannot, or wil not ſee their owne daunger in this caſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wolde call too remembraunce the example of coueteous Balam, whiche beinge ſo wiſe a Prophet, that he could ſe many thinges lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before to come vnto others yet bi loue and lokinge for the rewarde of wickednes, became much more <pb facs="tcp:176620:40"/>dulle and blind than a veri Aſſe, to ſee in his own wayes hys own dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. Nu .22. And I alſo aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which geue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng vſury vnto ſuche others, as wold haue an eaſy lyuing vpon o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther mens labours, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they make no cuſhens to lay vnder their elbows Eze .13. And that they be wel ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed afore they anſwere ſuch, as by the idol of couetous gaynes in their hartes do prouoke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anſwere ſo agreable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the filthi meaning of their own myndes, as is appertaynyng vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vtter perdicion of both the aſker &amp; the anſwerer. Ez 14. And finally I aduertiſe euery pryuate perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei learne of Acha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of Carmy not by vngodli gaines to polute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole finding of their familie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole ſtoke of their trade any y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in their handes, yea I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe <pb facs="tcp:176620:41"/>euery Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they deſyer to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agaynſte their enemyes afore god, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>member the word of god, my
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Alcan, by ioynyng vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> gaynes vnto hys own ſtuffe, had poluted al the Iſraelits ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they could not ſtande afore the face of their enemyes nor haue god to be wyth them, vntyll they had vtter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed oute that vngodlines fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongeſt them.</p>
            <p>The lord graunt, that charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble almes may vtterlye ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſh al couetous gaines from amongeſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Chriſtians. AMEN.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176620:41"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
